David McKain Papers
© 2006 University of Connecticut
David McKain Papers
undated, 1964-1997.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
McKain, David W.
3.25 linear feet.
David McKain is an award winning author and retired University of Connecticut faculty member (Avery Point Campus). McKain's papers contain manuscripts of edited and unedited written works, as well as professional correspondence and related documents.
MSS20040088
Biography
David McKain grew up in rural Pennsylvania (Bradford, PA), eventually attending the University of Connecticut. After a brief stint working for Holt, Rinehart & Winston and McGraw-Hill, McKain returned to the University of Connecticut to pursue his doctorate, which he completed in 1969. In addition to publication in numerous literary magazines such as Floating Bear, Evergreen Review, and Open Places, David McKain has edited two anthologies and published three volumes of his poetry: In Touch, The Common Life, and Spirit Bodies. While he has focused on poetry, his autobiography Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, won critical acclaim upon publication in 1988. Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country won the Associated Writing Programs Award for Non-fiction in 1987 and was nominated for a Pulitzer Prize. In his professional life, McKain has taught at the Avery Point campus of UConn, where he rose to the rank of full professor and was awarded 1983 Alumni Association Faculty Excellence in Teaching Award in 1983. He served as a visiting professor with his wife (Margaret Gibson) at Virginia Commonwealth University in 1989.
Published Works:
(Editor) Christianity: Some Non-Christian Appraisals, Mc-Graw-Hill, 1965.
(Editor) The Whole Earth: Essay in Appreciation, Anger, and Hope, St. Martin's, 1971.
In Touch, Ardis, 1975.
The Common Life, Alice James, 1982.
Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, University of Georgia Press, 1988; Simon & Schuster, 1990.
Spirit Bodies, Ithaca House, 1990.
Scope and Content
The bulk of the David McKain Papers contain manuscripts of edited and unedited written works. The remainder of the collection is professional correspondence and related documents. The collection includes materials from 1964- 1995.
Arrangement
Series I: Personal and Professional Papers ( 1964-1995 ) documents McKain's professional life at the University of Connecticut and his involvement in civic organizations. The bulk of this series is typescript manuscripts of correspondence and related documents.
Series II: Works ( undated, circa 1969-1991 ) contains typescript manuscripts with annotations and hand written notes for his poetry and his auto-biography Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country.
Series III: Print Ephemera ( 1964-1997 ) includes newspaper clippings and flyers. The clippings chronicle McKain's civic and professional life. The bulk of the clippings are reviews of McKain's books. The flyers advertise either his work or announce a reading of his work (often with his wife, Margaret Gibson).
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to literature, as well as the University, its history, faculty, and staff. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and is stored separately:
one photograph of David McKain, circa 1980.
The following materials have been separated from the collection and are cataloged separately:
Andover Bulletin, v. 79, #2, Fall 1995. Dodd Periodicals
Arizona Quarterly, v. 29, # 1, Spring 1973. Dodd Periodicals
AWP Chronicle, v. 23, #5, April 1991. Dodd Periodicals
Evergreen Review, No. 68, July 1969. Dodd Periodicals
Far Point, #1, Fall/Winter 1968. Dodd Periodicals
Letter Among Friends; A Quarterly of Poetry and Art, v. 5, #2, Spring 1983. Dodd Periodicals
Nadine, March 1972. Dodd
Occum Ridge Review, #16, Spring/Summer 1974. Dodd Periodicals
Open Places, #12-13, 16, May, 1972, Winter 1974. Dodd Periodicals
Poetry, v. 107, # 2, November 1965. Dodd Periodicals
Tar River Poetry, v. 26, #2, Spring 1987. Dodd Periodicals
University of Georgia Press Books for Fall 1988,. Dodd Periodicals
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
McKain, David W.
Organizations:
University of Connecticut.
Subjects:
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Publications.; Photographs.; Administrative Records.; Minutes.; Press releases.; School Records.; Fliers. [printed matter]; Manuscripts.; Galley proofs.; Typescripts.; Photocopies.; Notes.; Poems.; Newsletters.; Newspapers.; Broadsides.
Occupations:
Authors, American.; Educators, Connecticut.; College teachers, Connecticut.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by Dr. McKain in July 2004.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Series I: Personal and Professional Papers, 1964-1995
  - Correspondence while paperback editor at McGraw-Hill, 1964-1965 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Summary sheets for books edited by McKain at McGraw-Hill, 1964-1965 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and documents related to academic work, 1964-1992 (Box 1:, Folder 3-5)
  - Personal Correspondence, undated, 1989 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - Letters to the Editor (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - Awards, undated, 1978-1994 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - Letters from the World Prison Poetry Center re. Poetry readings, 1982-1983 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - Bradford High School Commencement Speech (Bradford, PA [hometown]), 1990 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - Environmental Education Committee (Groton, CT, 1971-1972 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
  - New London Organizing Council (New London, CT), circa 1976-1978 (Box 1:, Folder 12-14)
  - Voluntown Peace Trust (Voluntown, CT), 1980 (Box 1:, Folder 15-16)
  - Alice James Books, 1982-1983 (Box 1:, Folder 17)
  - Connecticut Poetry Circuit, 1990 (Box 1:, Folder 18)
  - "Wanderings" auto-biographical article in Contemporary Authors Autobiography Series Volume 14 (Box 1:, Folder 19)
  - The Day Writing Excellence Award (judge), 1990 (Box 1:, Folder 20)
- Series II: Works, undated, circa 1969-1991
  - Correspondence with magazine editors, circa 1965-1972 (Box 1:, Folder 21-22)
  - Correspondence with editors of poetry reviews, 1987-1989 (Box 1:, Folder 23)
  - The Whole Earth: Essays in Appreciation, Anger and Hope, notes and draft of editorial comments, 1971 (Box 1:, Folder 24)
  - The Whole Earth: Essays in Appreciation, Anger and Hope, related correspondence, 1971 (Box 1:, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence related to the publication of a proposed anthology of Connecticut poetry, 1974 (Box 1:, Folder 26)
  - In Touch, late draft, circa 1975 (Box 1:, Folder 27)
  - In Touch, manuscript, circa 1975 (Box 1:, Folder 28-30)
  - In Touch, letter from David Rigsbee, circa 1975 (Box 1:, Folder 31)
  - In Touch, review, circa 1975 (Box 1:, Folder 32)
  - In Touch ms with annotations, undated (Box 4:, Folder 167)
  - Christianity: Some Non-Christian Appraisals, letter from William Orr, 1979 (Box 1:, Folder 33)
  - Common Life, reviews and notes, circa 1982-1983 (Box 1:, Folder 34)
  - "Mountains Once More" early draft of "Windfall: Growing Up in the Alleghenies", circa 1985 (Box 1:, Folder 35)
  - "Mountains Once More" early draft (2) of "Windfall: Growing Up in the Alleghenies", circa 1985 (Box 1:, Folder 36)
  - "Windfall: Growing Up in the Alleghenies", letter from Donald Hall, 1985 (Box 1:, Folder 37)
  - Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, early notes (Box 1:, Folder 38)
  - "Death at Gowanda" early Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country draft (Box 1:, Folder 39)
  - Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, first draft ms with annotations, undated (Box 4:, Folder 163-166)
  - Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, early draft with notes and annotations, undated (Box 1:, Folder 40-43)
  - Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, early draft with notes and annotations, circa 1985 (Box 1:, Folder 44-56)
  - Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, early draft with notes and annotations, circa 1985 (Box 2:, Folder 57-72)
  - Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, working draft with notes, pages 1-95, circa December 1986 (Box 2:, Folder 73)
  - Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, working draft with notes, pages 96-157, circa December 1986 (Box 2:, Folder 74)
  - Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, working draft with notes, pages 158-234, circa December 1986 (Box 2:, Folder 75)
  - Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, working draft with notes, pages 235-294, circa December 1986 (Box 2:, Folder 76)
  - Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, working draft with notes, pages 295-315, circa December 1986 (Box 2:, Folder 77)
  - Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, working draft with notes, pages 316-334, circa December 1986 (Box 2:, Folder 78)
  - Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, working draft with notes, revisions of chapters, circa December 1986 (Box 2:, Folder 79)
  - Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, working draft with notes, revisions of chapters, circa December 1986 (Box 2:, Folder 80)
  - Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, reviews and correspondence pre-publication (Box 2:, Folder 81)
  - Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, final draft, pages 1-32 (Box 2:, Folder 82)
  - Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, final draft, pages 33-72 (Box 2:, Folder 83)
  - Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, final draft, pages 73-114 (Box 2:, Folder 84)
  - Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, final draft, pages 115-158 (Box 2:, Folder 85)
  - Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, final draft, pages 159-208 (Box 2:, Folder 86)
  - Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, final draft, pages 209-249 (Box 2:, Folder 87)
  - Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, final draft, pages 250-292 (Box 2:, Folder 88)
  - Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, final draft, pages 293-335 (Box 2:, Folder 89)
  - Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, publisher's working copy, pages 1-36 (Box 2:, Folder 90)
  - Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, publisher's working copy, pages 37-101 (Box 2:, Folder 91)
  - Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, publisher's working copy, pages 102-171 (Box 2:, Folder 92)
  - Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, publisher's working copy, pages 172-230 (Box 2:, Folder 93)
  - Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, publisher's working copy, pages 231-279 (Box 2:, Folder 94)
  - Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, publisher's working copy, pages 280-335 (Box 2:, Folder 95)
  - Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, related letters (Box 2:, Folder 96-100)
  - Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, correspondence with University of Georgia Press, 1988-1989 (Box 2:, Folder 101)
  - Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, paperback cover, undated (Box 3:, Folder 156)
  - Screenplay of Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country, circa 1993 (Box 4:, Folder 159)
  - Spirit Bodies, drafts of poems (Box 3:, Folder 102-122)
  - Spirit Bodies, late version (Box 3:, Folder 123-124)
  - Spirit Bodies, typescript manuscript, circa 1989 (Box 3:, Folder 125-128)
  - Spirit Bodies, reviews and related correspondence, 1987, 1991 (Box 3:, Folder 129)
  - Spirit Bodies ms with annotations, undated (Box 4:, Folder 162)
  - Correspondence with publishers, 1968-1990 (Box 3:, Folder 130)
  - "A place of loss and evil" (review of A Hole in the Wood: An America Boyhood by Richard Rhodes Chicago Tribune, 1990 October 7 (Box 3:, Folder 131)
  - Belonging proposal, circa 1995 (Box 3:, Folder 132)
  - Belonging, research proposal, undated (Box 3:, Folder 157)
  - "Empedocles on Etna: Arnold As Poet and Critic", undated (Box 3:, Folder 133)
  - "Learning to think big" (review of The Revolution of Little Girls by Blance Boyd) The Day (Box 3:, Folder 134)
  - "Poetry of Ron Padgett", undated (Box 3:, Folder 135)
  - "Poetry of Ron Phelps", undated (Box 3:, Folder 136)
  - "School: Work and Leisure As One", undated (Box 3:, Folder 137)
  - "The Human Face of Poetry", undated (Box 3:, Folder 138)
  - "The Rich are Putting the Middle..." (Box 3:, Folder 139)
  - Doctrine of the Hands ms with annotations, undated (Box 4:, Folder 160)
  - Doctrine of the Hands ms with annotations and notes, undated (Box 4:, Folder 161)
  - The Invention of Honey (unpublished collection of poetry), early related poems, undated (Box 3:, Folder 140-142)
  - The Invention of Honey (unpublished collection of poetry), undated (Box 3:, Folder 143-144)
  - Waters (unpublished collection of poetry), undated (Box 3:, Folder 145)
  - Review of My Father's Cabin: A Tale of Life, Love, Loss, and Land in Common Review Vol. 1 No. 4, undated (Box 3:, Folder 158)
  - Various Poems, undated (Box 3:, Folder 146)
  - Poetry Broadsides
    - Broadsides--"The Tremor", "The Meeting", "The Silent Motif", excerpt from Spellbound: Growing Up in God's Country and "Old Age", 1974 (Box 3:, Folder 147)
    - "Tracks", undated
- Series III: Print Ephemera, 1964-1997
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1964-1967 (Box 3:, Folder 148)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1988 (Box 3:, Folder 149)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1989 (Box 3:, Folder 150)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 151)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1991 (Box 3:, Folder 152)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1992-1997 (Box 3:, Folder 153)
  - Newspaper Clippings, undated (Box 3:, Folder 154)
  - Flyers, undated (Box 3:, Folder 155)